Guide to the Alexander Anderson Print Collection 1791-1907 PR 216
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Alexander Anderson Print Collection
1791-1907
PR 216
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.6 Linear feet (4 boxes, 1 drawer)
Most of the collection consists of works by Anderson, 1791-1864; there are also some scrapbooks kept by members of Anderson's family with examples of his wood engravings pasted in, engravings by his daughter, Ann Anderson Maverick, and some miscellaneous documentation. Apart from the scrapbooks, the bulk of the collection is wood engravings after scenes by European artists, trade cards, book illustrations, vignette engravings, and medical engravings.
Provenance
The collection is composed of multiple gifts, Much of the material was a gift of Daniel Parish in 1912
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Alexander Anderson was born in New York City on April 21, 1775. His father John Anderson was a printer. Alexander Anderson learned the art of engraving at a young age, and by 1797 he became one of the first Americans to undertake the practice of engraving on the end-grain of wood.
Anderson showed an early interest in medical drawings, and was apprenticed to a doctor at age fourteen. Subsequently, Anderson attended Columbia College to study medicine; he paid for his classes largely by selling engravings, which he made in his spare time. After graduating, he briefly practiced medicine, but became disenchanted with the profession. Anderson turned to engraving full time in 1798. For a short time he ran a store in which only children's books were sold, the first such specialized store in America. Anderson's engravings illustrated many books sold in New York, primarily American editions of English works.
After his first wife Ann and infant son died of yellow fever in 1798, Anderson was married to Jane Van Vleck in 1800. Together they had six children: John, Emmeline (later Mrs. Maibe), Ann (later Mrs. Andrew Maverick), Julia (later Mrs. Vincent M. Halsey), Mary (later Mrs. Skillman), and Jane (later Mrs. Edwin Lewis).
Anderson died on January 17, 1870.
Source:
Pomeroy, Jane. Alexander Anderson's Life and Engravings, with a Checklist of Publications drawn from His Diary. Worcester: American Antiquarian Society, 1990.
Scope and Content Note
The Alexander Anderson Print Collection spans the period from 1791 to the 1860s and primarily contains works by Anderson. The bulk of the collection is wood engravings after scenes by European artists, trade cards, vignette engravings, medical engravings, and scrapbooks kept by Anderson's family members with examples of his wood engravings pasted in. Some material is quite small, so the engravings have generally been separated by size. The collection includes several pen and ink drawings, as well as some watercolors, by Anderson. The collection is arranged in four series: Works by Anderson; Scrapbooks of Anderson's Work; Works by Others; and Documentation.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Works by Anderson
Series II. Scrapbooks of Anderson's Work
Series III. Works by Others
Series IV. Documentation
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
Three hundred and seventy eight original woodblocks engraved by Anderson are in the Printing Plate File (PR 057). Several engravings by Anderson, including a unique 1800 print, "Wheel of Fortune," are in the Issachar Cozzens Portfolio Print Collection (PR 145). A broadside featuring an image Anderson engraved in 1793 for the American Museum is in the N-YHS Library. The N-YHS Manuscripts Department holds a collection of Anderson's papers.
Columbia College (New York, N.Y.); Maverick, Ann Anderson, ca. 1810-1863; Certificates; Drawings; Illustrations; Marriage certificates; Medicine and art; Tickets; Trade cards; Vignettes; Watercolors; Wood engravings
- Series I: Works by Anderson
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I spans the period from 1791 when Anderson was a medical student to 1864, only a few years before his death. The series is arranged into two subseries: Engravings; and Drawings and Paintings.
  Engravings included here are generally illustrations, certificates, and other documents. Two large prints Anderson engraved after European artists Johannes Ridinger and David Teniers both date from 1818. A copy of one of these, Teniers' "Water Fowl," is printed on silk. Most of Anderson's other engravings were small, either vignettes or illustrations for books. These have mostly survived as small paper scraps cut from the original publication, and illustrate biblical scenes, animals from encyclopedia entries, and other subjects.
  Anderson's medical illustrations are well-represented. A wood engraving of a male skeleton, measuring over 36 inches high, is a unique print. Anderson reported copying the skeleton design from an edition of anatomical drawings by Bernard Albinus (1653-1721). An engraved male anatomical figure, measuring 42 by 13 inches, is one of three copies known to exist.
  One folder contains Anderson-related material that once belonged to Benson Lossing, one of Anderson's admirers and biographers. This folder includes thirty-five engravings, a carte-de-visite portrait of Anderson's second wife, Anderson's business card, and letters from Anderson and his wife to Lossing. This material was purchased together by the Society and has thus been kept together.
  Engraved documents include Anderson's admission tickets to medical classes at Columbia College. As a student, he received a commission to engrave these small cards with the names of the classes and professors printed on them. Also included here are two small engravings commemorating an undated Columbia College commencement ceremony.
  A wedding certificate for the wedding of Miss Frances Huntington to Josiah Phillips Quincy, on December 23, 1858, is also present.
  A program from a Festival of St. Nicholas celebration held at the New-York Historical Society in 1864 tells the story of the first such celebration in 1810 in which Dr. Anderson was feted. The program is illustrated with Anderson's engraving of John Pintard, librarian of the Society, and a self-portrait.
  Drawings and Paintings found in this series include eleven original pen and ink and watercolor drawings by Anderson. Medical subjects include images of vertebrae, muscle cutaways, and a neck abscess. Two watercolors show the Caribbean island of St. Vincent, where Anderson journeyed in 1798 after the death of his wife, to visit his uncle Alexander, who was the director of the Botanic Garden on the island. One drawing is a design for an emblem for the "Journeymen Stone-Cutter's Society."
  - Subseries I. Engravings
    - Illustrations
      - "Belmead," print mounted on wood block, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Return[ing] from the Boar Hunt," after Johannes Ridinger, 1818
        General note
        See Box 2, folder 21
      - "Water Fowl," after David Teniers., 1818
        See Box 2, folder 22
      - Book Illustrations--Biblical scenes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - Book Illustrations--General, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - Medical illustrations, [1794]-1800 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        See also oversize Folders 26 and 27
      - Vignette engravings, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
        See also: Box 2 folder 23
      - Miscellaneous engravings, mostly animals, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous engravings, once owned by Bernard Lossing, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Documents
      - Festival of St. Nicholas Program, 1864
        See Box 2, folder 24
      - Trade cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Tickets of Admission/Columbia College, [1794-1799] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Wedding certificate, 1858
        See Box 2, folder 25
  - Subseries II. Drawings and Paintings
    - Design for Stone Cutter's Society, pen and ink, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Medical drawings, [1795-1800] (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Watercolor, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Scrapbooks
  Series II. Scrapbooks contains two volumes which span the period from ca. 1810 to ca. 1860. One scrapbook, the smaller one of the two, is bound in red leather and inscribed "Miss Julia Anderson" on the cover. On the inside cover is inscribed in ink, "Alexander Anderson Halsey. From his father, April 1st 1872." Alexander Anderson Halsey was the son of Anderson's daughter Julia. This scrapbook contains examples of Anderson's wood engravings, often three or more per page. Some of these engravings have been annotated by an unknown hand, with captions such as "Rochester as it appeared in the year 1812." Another engraving has been annotated "I saw Grandfather engrave this in 1853, when I was 10 years old-Mary E. Halsey," suggesting that Mary Emmeline Halsey acquired the scrapbook from her brother Alexander. There is also one watercolor of a waterfall by Anderson pasted in. The last nine pages of the book contain wood engravings by Ann Anderson Maverick, Anderson's daughter.
  A larger scrapbook is titled on its spine, "Scrapbook of engravings by Dr. A. Anderson. Collected by his daughter, Mrs. Mabie, with additions by his granddaughter, Mary Emmeline Halsey." This scrapbook includes portraits of Indians, book illustrations (including illustrations from Shakespeare and the Bible), vignettes, bookplates, and business cards.
  - Scrapbook, "Miss Julia Anderson" on cover, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Scrapbook of engravings by Dr. A. Anderson", undated
    See: Box 3
- Series III: Works by Others
  Series III. Works by Others includes two folders of material that is not by Anderson. These are included here because they were given along with material that became the heart of this collection, and are either works picturing Anderson, or created by other members of his family. An 1887 pen drawing by E. C. Lewis is a copy of a self-portrait Anderson engraved on wood. One folder contains an engraving by Anderson's daughter, Ann Anderson Maverick (ca. 1810-1863), several by her husband Andrew's uncle, Peter Maverick (1780-1831), and an engraving by Peter's daughter, Emily Maverick Stoutenburgh (1803-1850). These engravings were in the possession of Mary Emmeline Halsey, Anderson's granddaughter and were given with the rest of her Anderson material.
  - Drawing of Anderson by E. C. Lewis, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Engraving by Ann Anderson Maverick, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Engraving by Peter Maverick, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Engraving by Emily Maverick Stoutenburgh, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Unsigned engravings, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Documentation
  Series IV includes a letter from Anderson's granddaughter Mary Emmeline Halsey to Daniel Parish, which discusses Anderson material in her possession, and that which had been bought from her by Parish (who later donated it to the Society to form this collection.) A set of seven of Alexander Anderson's engraving tools is included here, as is an albumen photograph of the tools photographed by F. M. Burr and presented to the Historical Society in 1886.
  - Anderson's engraving tools
    See: Box 4
  - Photograph of Anderson's engraving tools, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Mary Emmeline Halsey to Daniel Parish, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Oversize Material
  - From Series I. Works by Anderson
    - Engravings
      - "Return[ing] from the Boar Hunt," after Johannes Ridinger, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        Three copies
      - "Water Fowl," after David Teniers, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        Two copies.
      - Vignette engravings, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Festival of St. Nicholas Program, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Wedding certificate, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - From Series II. Scrapbooks
    - "Scrapbook of engravings by Dr. A. Anderson", undated (Box 3)
  - From Series IV. Documentation and Tools
    - Anderson's engraving tools (Box 4)
- Oversize Material Stored Flat
  These prints are housed in a flat file drawer.
  - [Male anatomical figure], 1799 (Folder 26)
  - [Skeleton after Albinus], 1798 (Folder 27)